Thanks so much, Joe. Really grateful for
the opportunity to be here and talk more
about the different approaches, especially
in the context of how do we start with
individual rights, think about the policy
before we rush to the technology, right?
Because there's an implicit social
contract, right? That is the use of these
digital identity systems. And it is much
better for that to be an explicit one
rather than one that is the most
convenient or imposed or anything else.
else, right? So I think we're all here for
the same thing. And being able to move
towards that, I have a pretty nerdy quote
actually that I want to start with from a
fantasy novel by Brandon Sanderson. Then
be wise about it. There are two kinds of
important people, Shallan. Some, when the
boulder of time rolls towards them, plant
themselves before it and throughout their
hands. All their lives they've been told
how great they are. They assume the world
itself will bend to their whims as a
caregiver once did when fetching a fresh
cup of milk. Those people end up squished.
Others step to the side as the boulder
passes, but are quick to say, see what I
did? I made it roll there. Don't make me
do it again. These are the ones who get
everyone else squished. Is there not a
third type of person? There is, but they
are rare. These know they can't stop the
boulder. They walk beside it, study it,
and bide their time. Then they nudge it
ever so slightly to bend its path. These
are the ones who actually changed the
world, and they terrify me for people
never see as far as they think they do.
And I think the wisdom in that is it takes
a diversity of thought approaches and use
cases and opinions to actually consider
all the different facets of this. It's an
enormously complex and ambitious
undertaking to build digital identity in a
way that minimizes the harms, but we're
able to derive most of the benefits. So
I'm really happy that we're in a room with
a ton of diverse thinkers from people who
are experts on individual rights, what
constituents care about, what people
actually feel, the technology itself,
including the cryptography, security and
privacy aspects of it, adoption, change
management and user experience. So I think
that we're very excited to show how these
concepts from SEDI where you start with
the policy and the rights and then the
technology is figured out after that.
That's really what we want to showcase and
how it can help our existing investments
we can derive value from those. And
especially as we saw with the adoption,
MDL is in I think 17 states at this point.
A lot of investment, a lot of great
security people have been thinking about
that model. The TSA spent over $250
million on machines that can accept the
MDL. So is that all to waste if it doesn't
comply? Or what are we thinking about
here? What about everything else? And
fortunately, you might even be able to
shed some more light on this. Yeah.
Thanks, Soren. And thanks for taking all
our five minutes. But it's been actually
an honor to work with Utah. Excellent
team, excellent people. It has been a
fantastic experience and we're really
happy, of course, with all the work that
they perform and we had the honor to
support them to have a successful MDL
issued and being used and utilized in many
not enough use cases and relying parties
including TSA and credit unions and law
enforcement. But we're happy to be also
part of this group that Chris put together
to assist the best we can with our
experience and knowledge and technology to
make whatever next steps Utah chooses to
take successful. So it's amazing. So what
are we seeing over there? That's a
verifier. A verifier is something a
relying party would have. A relying party
being anything, anyone that accepts and
consumes a digital identity and MDL. And
that can be a government agency that asks
for your ID. It can be law enforcement. It
can be anyone in the private sector. It
could be a bank, could be AIDS restricted
alcohol sales, tobacco, and so on.
Whenever they ask for that ID card of your
driver's license, you can present the MDL
or at least that is the purpose and you
can use verifiers as simple as an app or
in a fixed point with a scanner or
eventually online. All that technology
exists and hopefully it's going to be part
of the ecosystem we all operate in. Can
you talk about what's going to happen
between this SEDI wallet and And what kind
of, you know, how is the data transmitted?
What happens between this application
running on your phone and an application
that holds a credential on my phone? Well,
yeah, originally the ISO standard, which
is what the Utah MDL is complying to,
along with our close to 20 other
jurisdictions that issue an MDL that
complies to the ISO 18013-5, which is the
in-person standard. it had a phone home,
it had a connection to the system on
record that is no longer the case. And
similarly, any verification we would
conduct with a SEDI, it will only consume
whatever you have on the phone and you
present. – And it goes, this could work in
the mountains, right? If there's no
internet or anything. – Correct. It will
be done offline because again, it will
cryptographically analyze whatever you
have provisioned in your phone as your
digital identity. I always really like
this part where it goes over Bluetooth and
NFC proximity technologies that involve no
servers, right? It's just peer-to-peer
over device. That's actually the best
privacy profile you could hope for, right?
So there are parts that have had
extraordinary investments that are really
valuable from a privacy and usability
perspective. And what we see in that
wallet is not an MDL. There's no driving
privileges there. It is a credential that
is solely focused on identification,
right? And that the reason that it is a
SEDI credential is that it conforms to the
code in SEDI, right? Is the idea. So if we
start looking over here, I told you it
would be a nerdy presentation, right? We
looked in the Utah code, right? And there
is SEDI enshrined in it as statutes. And
when you click in, you're able to see the
different definitions, and requirement
from Senate Bill 260 that was signed into
law by Governor Cox earlier this spring.
And thank you to representative and
senator for the work and the whole
coalition. So it's really about controls.
It's really about these are the things
we're expecting this credential to do and
operate, right? That's what it represents.
So data formats, everything else, those
are things to figure out, but making it
policy-based and starting it from there is
the most important part because that is
the social contract, right? To express the
will of a people and have those as the
agreed upon controls if someone is to
participate in the system. So we just want
to demonstrate that this model, right, can
also work with the corpus of investment
for existing systems that have been
significant and growing in adoption. So we
have looked into the mobile driver's
license technical specification. Sure. We
have looked at the sub component called a
mobile document or an MDOT. And that is
just a data format. That doesn't describe
how to use it or anything else. And there
are other pieces that we can build up to
that we can agree with and are aligned to
the SEDI framework. So that is the idea
and what you're going to see with this
demonstration. – And similar, of course,
any digital identity, the benefits are
you're not using your card, you don't
share your card, you don't show any
information, it's not copied, you don't
flash past so-called whatever it is on the
phone. and it respects the privacy of the
user and you only share what you choose.
So if you want just your age to enter a
bar or alcohol sales, that's that is all
you share, not the entire ID. Unless of
course you're at a bank or you're applying
for a loan or law enforcement is asking
for the entire ID, that is when you share
if you choose the entire information.
That's right. And the MDOC data format
here point supports selective disclosure
as part of that base. We like that. We're
like, okay, that sounds pretty good. Let's
take that part. Right. So we're going to
demonstrate and there's no contact. You
can do it's a QR barcode scanning. It is
via Bluetooth through a good range or a
tap NFC just like as everyone is familiar
with the Apple pay and so on. Yep. So
let's say that we're in a use case where
let's call it law enforcement. Let's say
there is warranted ability to request
information, right? So there's going to be
a lot of it being requested. – So you can
see there it says all info. So I'm asking
for all of the information from the user.
– But this can be tailored to different
profiles depending on the context. And
that's the really important policy work we
need help with to figure out. So I'm going
to share the identity by creating a QR
code. You can either tap or create a QR
code to share it. What it does is it
brokers a secure connection over
Bluetooth. So it adds encryption on top of
Bluetooth because Bluetooth itself has
challenges. That's how the MDL protocol
worked. That part of the MDOC and standard
seemed to be pretty promising. And we were
able to show a QR code. So we're bringing
up the scanner. No contact.
And actually it's going to consume. I get
to decide what I share or not over here on
this screen. Those are the fields
requested. As the user, I get to make the
determination. That's another feature of
the protocol that was supported. And when
I press approve, it's transmitted over
basically the Bluetooth connection peer-to
-peer. So this would work in the mountains
without any kind of external connectivity,
right? And again, this is being used at a
ton of airports already, right? So we're
just able to make sure that that part of
the technology can also work for SEDI
credentials. – So you can see that I'm
seeing the information that he shared. I
can bring up the picture, do one last
visual check if I wish. And it has the
document information. So I know it's from
Utah, the document number and that's about
it. Yeah. – As simple as that. Plus, of
course, I have the verification on the age
verification. – Yeah. Well, let's say I'm
I'm at a bar right at night and I want to
show I'm over 21 but kind of don't want
you to know my full name and where I live,
my address, right? How do we do that? –
So, I will just the one that is asking for
the information can can ask only for the
age. So, unlike of what you choose, I can
only ask for the age and whatever you
share, I will only get the age. And of
course, as you saw, once my hey, I leave
that verified information I had is gone.
It's not saved. It's not tracked. None of
that. And you cannot get a screenshot.
Yeah. So the policy consideration here is
that there are many different attributes
that you could add to this thing and ask
for, right? So those are the really
important decisions to be made. Can we add
veteran status, disability rating? Can we
add how many dependents you have? These
are all really relevant for programs like
Wix and others that that require expedient
access, but we also want to eliminate the
fraud, right? So, and because it's the
user consenting to display the
information, you don't really have to go
with one of these very complex interagency
data sharing agreements if we faithfully
present an opportunity consent for people,
right? So, if it's tough to do across
agencies and coordinate, just give it to
the person and let them decide, right? All
right. So, I know your age. You're looking
too young to me. Thank you. Thank you.
Oh, is this the right one that you've
requested? Did you configure it to just
select the age only? – Just the age only.
– Well, see, now I have the opportunity to
deny all this stuff. – If you agree, I
want to deny all this new age. Try again?
– Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah.
Because there is an option also to request
I need find info or to project that one.
Right. Because that was on. Oh for age.
Okay. Yeah. Okay. So now I can let him in.
So you turn on the safety.
Let's see. Age over 18. Got a different
set of things requested. But you know
what? I'm really just going to get rid of
all these things except my portrait and
age. And that's all you're going to get.
And the Verify will have to deal with it.
So I think there is a setting where I've
definitely seen that work with this app
though. – You want to try again? – Sure. –
Let's give it an answer. Right.
And you say okay. So those are the only
data fields that ever left the wallet,
right? During that specific interaction.
So yeah. See us after will definitely show
that you can do an age demonstration. I
think that I have a version of the GT
mobile app where I can just ask for the
age of mine. But But you'll see other
profiles where we can get it. So great. We
have two more things to show you really
quickly. And one of them has to do… –
What's the floor? – Okay, great. – And
those I'm on setter by the way. – Yeah. –
Okay. – Welcome. Thank you. All right. So
the other two use cases.
One is banking and it's very important for
people to get access to financial
services. Many of the same methods are
more or less used for benefits
distribution when you're trying to figure
out eligibility and identity verification
for some of those things, right? So this
is a generally useful flow. In fact, NIST
has this National Cybersecurity Center of
Excellence, right? And we're trying to
figure out how are we going to do banking
KYC? privacy with the mobile driver's
license. I see some folks in here who are
actually formal participants in this
program. So that's great because a lot of
federal agencies and other states are
going to look to the output of this
program and how that's going to work.
There are a lot of banks, a lot of tech
companies, a lot of other actors, and
basically we're trying to figure out how
do we preserve privacy but also allow for
these kinds of use cases.
They're even talking about shapes that
it's going to work. But right now it's
just called the MDL program. There's no
reason why it needs to be. It could just
be digital identities, right? But that's
kind of the only thing that popped up,
right? So to have a credential that has
steady controls over it would be very
interesting, I think. But back to our
banking example, and this is where a lot
of tech companies have invested a ton of
effort. They're best UX people. their best
security folks. How do we make this really
good? And the interface is mostly for the
MDL, but those technologists have agreed
that, hey, other things might be
acceptable here. Passports, EIDs in Europe
are not driver's licenses, right? So MDL
isn't so strongly applicable in some
areas. So how do we allow a diversity of
different credential types to be accepted?
And there have been great strides in the
user experience towards this. So we're
going to basically open a fictitious bank
account.
And I'm also going to make sure that I can
show you what happens in the wallet
alongside that if I can figure out how to
make this small again. There we go. So
we're at Arch's bank. We're going to open
an account. We're going to begin our
banking application. and type in our
email. I'll just imagine that I get a
confirmation code. You've probably done
this before. Go to your email, you find
the code, you put it in. Multi-factor. So
right now it's a phone number, but you
know future approaches like pass keys and
digital credentials will hopefully leave
the need for this. So put a phone number
in there. Same deal. Again, many banking
systems just work like this today. And a
social security number is required by
FinCEN's customer identification program.
So that's a Bank Secrecy Act requirement.
So, you know, you'll just see it as a
requirement for banks. But at this stage,
it's part of identity verification, right?
And what a lot of institutions do today is
they say, hey, upload a picture of your
driver's license or upload a picture of
utility bill. And none of those security
features are actually valid when you just
take a picture of it, right? Like that's
the new world of security needs to be
built on things that AI is bad at. That's
showing up in person. That's breaking
cryptography, especially post-quantum
cryptography. That's making very complex
computational predictions about physics
and how light refracts on things or how
you know something can change
geometrically. And that's what a lot of
the liveness algorithms are about. But it
all starts with having a really strongly
certified credential. And when you want to
verify with it, then it uses the operating
system level controls to say, hey, do you
want to share your data? It's built on the
same technologies as passkeys, actually,
if you look under the hood. We want to
share it. QR code comes up. We see on the
wallet. I'll scan it. You won't be able to
see everything. I think there's some
privacy protections with the screen share,
but you'll be able to see the important
parts. So it tells me only connect to
devices you trust. And when I connect what
happens, you'll see a lower popover. This
is kind of like the Apple Pay experience
or the Google Pay experience. It's part of
the operating system and you get to pick
which wallet it comes out of, right?
You've been requested a credential from
somewhere. We're going to agree. And
again, we have that opportunity to consent
what gets sent, right? If we send it, then
what happens is instantaneously a
cryptographic payload is sent along with
the data fields and that can be verified
by a server. So it goes to from the phone
to the laptop, goes from the laptop to the
server, and then it gets verified way
easier and more secure than uploading all
those different documents. You submit and
you're good to go. So getting easy access
to financial services benefits a slew of
other things requires really good UX, but
we can't compromise on individual rights.
We can't compromise on security as we get
there, right? So let's take those existing
investments that companies put their best
UX and security people on and apply it to
a framework that is individual rights
driven, right? So that's the proposal for
ensuring backwards compatibility to a lot
of these systems. A lot of the time you
think legacy old experience, but these are
actually some really great experiences
happening, right? And the last thing I'll
show is interoperability with a completely
different system. This is the same
technology harness. Thank you for the
Veridian team for providing their issuance
portal for this part of the demo. So
different company, not Spruce ID. It's not
like one company built all this stuff.
These are interoperable protocols. And
there's something called the Global Legal
Entity Identifier Foundation that is able
to do identification for organizations to
a high degree of proofing so that we can
know who we're doing business with if a
company wants to get a benefit or
something else, right? So basically, I
want to have another credential on my
phone where I can have that employee badge
or proof that I'm part of an organization
Let's say I'm going to ask someone else
for a credential or I want to open a
business banking account. These are useful
to understand what entity I'm associated
with. What if you're part of LEO and you
want to show that you're a real cop and
you're not trying to just coerce someone
to do something, right? So you can issue a
credential for this. There's some numbers
as part of it. I'll put my name. We'll
just say employee and we'll issue the
credential. And this is a totally
different technology stack built on KERI
and ACDCs, which protocol and format
invented right here in Utah. You get to
accept it and a new credential shows up as
an official organization role. And then
when we want to go request it, we can
request a presentation from that wallet.
The wallets have been linked prior. It's a
demo. Request a presentation. We will see
the request happening and approving it.
We'll see the request is updated, right?
And these are different data formats
entirely, but following the same control
principles, right? So that's the end of my
demo. Thank you.